Okay, we're going to do דף זיין *Daf Zayin* now, the דף
*daf* we would have been doing on תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*. We're
pre-recording it and we pick up with טז עמוד ב *Tet Zayin
Amud Bet*.
Eight lines down from the wide lines. אין עושים עיר ir הנדחת
*Ein osin ir nidachas*, for an עיר הנדחת *ir nidachas* you need
a בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din* of 71. מנא הני מילי
*Mena hani mili*? אמר רבי Rebbe. חייא בר יוסף אמר רבי Rebbi,
אושעיא דאמר קרא *Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef amar Rabbi Oshaya d'amar
kra* והוצאת את האיש ההוא או את האשה ההיא אשר עשו את
הדבר הרע הזה אל שעריך *v'hotzeisa es ha-ish ha-hu o es ha-isha
ha-hi asher asu es ha-davar ha-ra ha-zeh el sharecha*. Individuals are judged
in the gates by the local
סנהדרין Sanhedrin, *Sanhedrin*, but the whole city, a רבים *rabbim*, is not
judged by a local סנהדרין Sanhedrin, *Sanhedrin* but by the סנהדרין גדולה
Sanhedrin Gedola *Sanhedrin Gedola*.
אין עושים עיר הנדחת
בספר *Ein osin ir nidachas b'sefar*. Now we're dealing with
some
of the laws of עיר הנדחת *ir nidachas*. You don't do it
on the border. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama? *Mai ta'ama*? מקרבך אמר רחמנא
*Mikirbecha amar Rachmana*,
in your midst, ולא מן הספר *v'lo min ha-sefar*, and not from
the border. It has to be in the middle of the land.
ולא שלש *V'lo shalosh*, and not three together, דכתיב אחת *dichtiv achas*,
it says in one of your cities. אבל עושין אחת או שתים
*Aval osin achas o shtayim*, but not only one, it can even
be two, דכתיב עריך *dichtiv arecha* in plural, your cities. תנו רבנן
Tanu Rabbanan, *Tanu rabanan*: אחת *Achas* means one. אחת *Achas*, ולא שלש
*v'lo shalosh*, and not three cities. אתה אומר אחת ולא שלש או
אינו אלא אחת ולא שתים *Ata omer achas v'lo shalosh o eino
ela achas v'lo shtayim*, maybe you can't even have two? כשהוא אומר
עריך *Keshehu omer arecha*, your cities in plural, הרי שתים אמור *harei
shtayim amur*. המני מקיים אחת *Ha-mani mekayem achas*? So עריך *arecha* is
two, so what does one exclude? אחת ולא שלש *Achas v'lo shalosh*,
it excludes three. וזימנין אמר רב בבית דין אחד הוא דאין עושים
הא בשנים ושלשה בתי דינים עושים *V'zimnin amar Rav b'Beis Din echad
hu d'ein osin ha b'shnayim u'shlosha batei dinin osin*. It means one
בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din* can't פסקן *pasken* on more than
one עיר הנדחת *ir nidachas*, but in different ones they can. Of
course the question is how do you get a different בית דין
beis din. *Beis Din* if it's all סנהדרין גדולה Sanhedrin Gedolah, *Sanhedrin
Gedola*? So רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* I think says, where's רש"י Rashi *Rashi*?
כל זמן שהסנהדרין זו קיימת *Kol zman she'ha-Sanhedrin zu kayamas*. אבל מתו
אלו ונתמנו אחרים עושים *Aval mesu elu v'nismanu acherim osin*. If it
was, you know, a different generation you could, everybody died. I don't
know how much everybody, how many people have to be replaced. But
anyway, on that you could do. וזימנין אמר רב ואפילו בשנים ושלשה
בתי דינים לעולם אין עושים *V'zimnin amar Rav v'afilu b'shnayim u'shlosha batei
dinin l'olam ein osin*. You could never do it. Or what does
that mean? Like never in the history of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*
could you have more than three עיר הנדחתס *ir nidachases*
I suppose. מאי טעמא דרב *Mai
ta'ama d'Rav*? משום קרחה *Mishum karcha*. Says it would leave a bald
spot in the land of Israel if you would do two or
three. Again, not exactly clear why that would mean that you could
never do it over a long period of time. All right, but
maybe within a certain period of time. אמר ריש לקיש לא שנו
אלא במקום אחד *Amar Reish Lakish lo shanu ela b'makom echad*. So
therefore the problem therefore of doing two or doing three is if
it's in one place. אבל בשנים ושלשה מקומות עושים *Aval b'shnayim u'shlosha
mekomos osin*. If the problem is leaving a bald spot, right, then
two or three separate places you could do. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
אמר אין עושים משום קרחה *Rabbi Yochanan amar ein osin mishum karcha*.
No, it's a problem of קרחה *karcha*. Which seems, again, it's not
exactly clear if they're debating. Is that the same point? So it's
that and therefore it's a problem only in one place. תניא tanya,
כוותיה דרבי יוחנן אין עושים שלש עיירות מנודחות בארץ ישראל *Tanya k'vasei
d'Rabbi Yochanan ein osin shalosh ayaros menudachos b'Eretz Yisrael*. אבל עושים אותם
שתים כגון אחת ביהודה ואחת בגליל *Aval osin osam shtayim k'gon achas
b'Yehuda v'achas ba-Galil*.
In different places you can separate. אבל שתים ביהודה ושתים בגליל אין
עושים *Aval shtayim b'Yehuda u'shtayim ba-Galil ein osin*. That you can't do
because of the קרחה *karcha* point. It seems like the קרחה *karcha*
point is not to tell you that the three can't be קרחה
*karcha*, but you can never do even two in one place, okay,
and that's because of this קרחה *karcha* idea. So there's a different
idea. There's one an idea of three which might even be spread
out, that's from the אחת ולא שלש *achas v'lo shalosh*, and then
there's a קרחה *karcha* idea that you can't have two in the
same place, but you could have it spread out. אבל עושים אותם
שתים כגון אחת ביהודה ואחת בגליל שתים ביהודה ושתים בגליל אין עושים
*Aval osin osam shtayim k'gon achas b'Yehuda v'achas ba-Galil shtayim b'Yehuda u'shtayim
ba-Galil ein osin*. That you can't do because of the קרחה *karcha*.
הסמוכה לספר אפילו אחת אין עושים *Ha-semucha la-sefar afilu achas ein osin*.
On the border even one, מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*, why? שמא ישמעו
נכרים ויחריבו את ארץ ישראל *shema yishmu nochrim v'yacharivu es Eretz Yisrael*
because it exposes the land of Israel to enemies. והא מקרבך אמר
רחמנא ולא מן הספר *V'ha mikirbecha amar Rachmana v'lo min ha-sefar*? Why
do you have to give a sort of a rational reason if
it's a גזירת הכתוב *g'zeiras ha-kasuv*? It says in your midst, the
middle of the land. רבי Rebbi. שמעון Shimon, הוא דדרש טעמא דקרא
*Rabbi Shimon hu d'darash ta'ama d'kra*. Yeah, you're right, it's based on
the פסוק *pasuk*, but this is רבי Rebbi. שמעון Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*
who explicates the reason behind the פסוקים *psukim*. Now normally רבי Rabbi.
שמעון Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* sort of I try to identify the reason
and use that to shape the halachic parameters. Here it just seems
like he's just giving a reason and it's not halachically meaningful. But
maybe he means because he's motivated from this concern of אויבים *oyvim*
that pushes him to interpret the word מקרבך *mikirbecha* the way he
does. סנהדרי גדולה היתה ע"א *Sanhedri Gedola haysa ayin aleph*. Now the
big סנהדרין Sanhedrin. *Sanhedrin* was 71. מאי טעמא דרבנן דאמרי משה Moshe
על גביהם *Mai ta'ama d'rabanan d'amri Moshe al gabeihem*?
Why do the rabbis say count משה Moshe *Moshe*? What's the debate
whether to count משה Moshe *Moshe* or not? אמר קרא amar kra
והתיצבו שם עמך *Amar kra v'hisyatzvu sham imach* by the 70 elders
let them stand there with you. עמך ואתה עמהם *Imach v'ata imahem*,
you're with them, you're part of the group. לרבי יהודה *L'Rabbi Yehuda*,
what would he... עמך משום שכינה. Shechina No, no, you're there so
that the שכינה flows through you to them, but it doesn't mean
that you're part of the same group. רבנן Rabbanan אמר קרא ונשאו
אתך במשא העם. v'nasu itach b'masa ha'am. They carry with you. So
everybody together, the 70 of them plus one of you carries the
burden, so it's a group of 71.
אתך ואת בהדייהו, itach v'at bahadaya, you with them. רבי יהודה: Rabbi
Yehuda: אתך בדומים לך. itach b'domeh lach. No, it means that they
have to be similar to you in terms of personal character, wisdom,
as much as possible, but not that you're part of the same
group. ואצלתי מן הרוח אשר עליך ושמתי עליהם ונשאו אתך ve'okalet meh'alecha
v'nasu itach na. But we already have another אתך itach by יתרו
Yitro that says that you have to be try to strive to
be like Moshe, so this extra אתך itach says Moshe's part of
the group and that's 71. ואלפי v'alpiz
and that's by סנהדרין Sanhedrin גדולה and סנהדרין קטנה. Sanhedrin Ketana. That's
by יתרו, Yitro, that's a small סנהדרין, Sanhedrin but if you have
that aspect of אתך itach being like Moshe by the small סנהדרין,
Sanhedrin. certainly by the big סנהדרין. Sanhedrin So the extra אתך itach
here says that it becomes a בית דין beis din of 71.
Okay. Now we're going to deal with the selection of the בית
דין beis din of the 70
and paralleling what we saw in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan our rabbis taught,
וישארו שני אנשים במחנה. v'yisharu shnei anashim bamachaneh. יש אומרים בקלפי נשתיירו,
yesh omrim bakalfi nishtayeru, that as a result of the drawing of
the lots. שבשעה שאמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה: shebesha'ah she'amar lo
Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Moshe: אספה לי שבעים איש מזקני ישראל, esfa li
shiv'im ish miziknei Yisrael, collect 70, אמר משה, amar Moshe, כיצד אעשה?
keitzad e'eseh? What should I do? עבר ששה מכל שבט, ever shisha
m'kol shevet, נמצאו שנים יתירים, nimtzu shnayim yeteirim, so that's 72.
עבר חמשה חמשה מכל שבט, ever chamisha chamisha m'kol shevet, נמצאו עשרה
חסירים, nimtzu asara chaseirim, 60, 10 short.
עבר ששה משבט וחמשה משבט ever shisha mishevet ve-chamisha mishevet and identify
two tribes that are only going to give five, הרי אני מטיל
קנאה בין השבטים, harei ani matil kina bein hashvatim, that's going to
be jealousy. מה עשה, mah asah, what did he do? בירר ששה
ששה, berer shisha shisha, he selected six from each tribe, so there
are 72 potential candidates. והביא שבעים ושנים פתקין ve'heivi shiv'im u'shnayim pitkin
and he made 72 lots. על שבעים כתב זקן, al shiv'im katav
Zaken, on 70 he wrote elder, ושנים הניח חלקים, u-shnayim hiniach halakin,
and two blank.
בללם ונתנם בקלפי, bil'alam v'natanam bakalfi, he mixed them up and put
them in a box. אמר להם, amar lahem, באו וטלו פתקיכם, bou
u-telu pitkeichem, come and draw your lots. כל מי שעלה בידו זקן,
kol mi she'alah beyado Zaken, אמר כבר נתקדש שמים. amar kvar nishkadesh
shamayim. Everybody said זקן, Zaken, they said heaven has already sanctified. What's
interesting, the line in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is מנוחה, minucha, they've appointed
you. The word מינוי minuy is a very central word for דיין.
dayan. Anyway, כל מי שעלה בידו חלק,
kol mi
she'alah beyado chalak, if it was blank, אמר המקום לא חפץ בך,
amar Hamakom lo chafetz becha, sorry gabba, God doesn't want you. אני
מה אעשה לך? ani mah e'eseh lach? I can't help you, it's
not my fault.
כיוצא בדבר אתה אומר, k'yotzei vadavar atah omer, similarly it says ולקחת
חמש חמש שקלים לגלגלת,
velakachta chamesh chamesh shekalim
lagulgolet, five shekel for the 273 extra בכורות bechorim over the כהנים.
Kohanim. The כהנים Kohanim redeemed the בכורות, bechorim, but there were 273
extra. אמר משה, amar Moshe, כיצד אעשה להם לישראל? keitzad e'eseh l'hem
l'Yisrael? What should I do for them? אם אומר להם תנו פדיונכם
וצאו, im omar lahem tenu pidyonchem u-tzo, if I say to one
of the בכורות bechorim give your five shekel and go, יאמר לי
כבר נפדיתי על ידי בן לוי. yomar li kvar nifdaiti al yedei
ben Levi. No, a בן לוי ben Levi corresponds to me. So
how do I identify the ones that don't have a בן לוי
ben Levi to correspond to them? מה עשה, mah asah, what did
he do?
הביא עשרים ושנים אלף פתקין, heivi esrim u-shnayim elef pitkin, he brought
22,000
lots, וכתב עליהם בן לוי. ve-katav aleihem ben Levi. ועל שלשה ושבעים
ומאתים כתב עליהם חמש שקלים, ve'al shlosha ve-shiv'im u-matayim katav aleihem chamesh
shekalim, and on 273 he wrote five shekel. בללם ונתנם בקלפי, bil'alam
v'natanam bakalfi, he mixed them, put them in a box. אמר להם,
amar lahem, טלו פתקיכם, tlu pitkeichem, draw your lots. מי שעלה בידו
בן לוי, mi she'alah beyado ben Levi, אמר לו פטר דאחא בן
לוי, amar lo pattar de-acha ben Levi, he says, so you've got
בן לוי, ben Levi, you're redeemed by a בן לוי. ben Levi.
מי שעלה בידו חמש שקלים, mi she'alah beyado chamesh shekalim, אמר לו
תן פדיונך וצא, amar lo ten pidyoncha ve-tze, give your redemption and
go.
Okay, so that's one answer, that they were left because they drew
the blanks. Now it sounds like they were left because they drew
the blanks, right? אלדד ומידד, Eldad u-Medad, they were drawn by the
קלפי. kalfi. But רש"י, Rashi you know רש"י Rashi on the תורה
Torah says, no, they didn't draw the blanks, they saw that the
people that drew the blanks were going to go and say they
had the word זקן Zaken and they stayed back so as not
to embarrass them. That's not in this גמרא. Gemara. If you look
closely at רש"י Rashi here, four lines down in the narrow lines,
מי שעלה בידו חלק, mi she'alah beyado chalak, רש"י Rashi says,
ושנים מאותו שבעים שהלכו ליטול עלה בידו חלק ונשתיירו שני פתקין שהיו
כתובים בקלפי שהיו אצל אלדד ומידד שלא הלכו
ליטול שמתיירא שלא יעלה בידם חלק.
u-shnayim me'oto shiv'im shehalchu litol alu beyado chalak, ve'nishtayeru shnei pitkin shehayu
ktuvim bakalfi shehayu eitzel Eldad u-Medad
shelo halchu litol, shemityarei shelo ya'aleh beyadam chalak. So what רש"י says
here is not that they were like צדיקים, tzaddikim, they didn't want
to draw because they didn't want it to come up blank. So
they'd rather remove themselves from the lottery than risk drawing blank and
having this line like המקום לא חפץ בך. Hamakom lo chafetz becha.
They'd rather eliminate themselves. You know, sadly there are people like that
that sometimes like rather, you know, they don't want to put themselves
out there, so they already sort of decided that they're not going
to enter into the contest. Wayne Gretzky has the line which is
you miss 100 percent of the shots that you never take. So,
you know, this is a different version and it doesn't make them
the same type of צדיקים tzaddikim as the other sort of version
does. But anyway, that's one thing because of the luck. So now
back to the גמרא. Gemara.
רבי שמעון אומר... Rabbi Shimon omer... מחנה נשתיירו. machne nishta'iru. They actually
chose without this whole show of the lot to stay in the
camp. בשעה שאמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה besha'ah she'amar lo Hakadosh
Baruch Hu l'Moshe אצלי שבעים איש etzli shivim ish taking seventy. אמר
אלדד ומידד: Amar Eldad uMedad: איננו ראויים לאותה גדולה. einenu re'uyim l'ota
gedolah. We're not deserving of this greatness. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא: Amar
Hakadosh Baruch Hu: הואיל ומיעטתם עצמכם ho'il u'mi'atatem atzmechem because you have
shrank yourself, made yourself small, maybe they also eliminated the need for
the lots once they publicly said we're withdrawing.
הריני מוסיף גדולה על גדולתכם. hareini mosif gedolah al gedulatchem. I will
give you even greater greatness than you would have had.
מה גדולה הוסיף להם? ma gedolah hosif lahem? What was the greatness?
All the other נביאים, nevi'im, meaning the other seventy elders, it says
ויתנבאו ולא יספו. vayitnabu velo yasafu. So הנביאים כולם hanevi'im kulam נתנבאו
ופסקו, nitnabu v'pasaku, their נבואה nevuah stopped. הם נתנבאו ולא פסקו. hem
nitnabu velo pasaku. They did it. ויתנבאו ולא יספו, vayitnabu velo yasafu,
excuse me, that was by דתן
ואבירם.
Datan
v'Aviram. Oh no, I'm sorry, getting it mixed up. Anyway, it was
they were מתנבאים בתוך המחנה. mitnabim betoch hamachane. And for them, it
did not stop and for the others it stopped. And how do
you know that?
ומה נבואה נתנבאו? u'ma nevuah nitnabu? First, what was the prophecy that
they gave in the camp? Then יהושע Yehoshua got all upset. אמרו,
amru, they said: משה מת ויהושע מכניס את ישראל לארץ. Moshe met
v'Yehoshua machnis et Yisrael l'aretz. משה Moshe will die and יהושע Yehoshua
will bring the people in. The גמרא's Gemara going to say that
presumably is inferred from the fact that יהושע Yehoshua was defending משה's
Moshe honor and משה Moshe said: המקנא אתה לי? hamkana ata li?
So clearly there was some defending of his honor going on.
אבא חנין אמר משום רבי אליעזר: Abba Chanin amar mishum Rabbi Eliezer:
על עסקי שליו הם נתנבאו. al iskei slav hem nitnabu. עלי שליו
עלי שליו. ali slav, ali slav. They were prophesying that the שליו
slav would come.
רב נחמן אמר על עסקי גוג ומגוג היו מתנבאים. Rav Nachman amar
al iskei Gog u'Magog hayu mitnabim. No, that future ultimate war of
Armageddon. שנאמר: shene'emar: כה אמר ה' אלוקים האתה הוא אשר דברתי בימים
קדמונים ביד עבדי נביאי ישראל. Koh amar Hashem Elokim: ha'atah hu asher
dibarti b'yamim kadmonim beyad avdai nevi'ei Yisrael. Did I only speak once
to my previous servants the prophets, הנביאים בימים ההם שנים hanevi'im bayamim
hahem shanim
that prophesied in those days שנים shanim in those years להביא אותך
עליהם l'havi otcha aleihem that I would bring this
terrible war against you? The war of גוג ומגוג. Gog u'Magog. אל
תקרי שנים אלא שניים. Al tikrei shanim ela shnayim. Not years, but
two. Two prophets. ואיזה הם שניים נביאים שנתנבאו בכרך אחד נבואה אחת?
v'eizeh hem shnayim nevi'im shenitnabu becherach echad nevuah achat? What two prophets
prophesied at the same time, the same prophecy and the same prophecy?
הוי אומר אלדד ומידד. Hevei omer Eldad uMedad. That's how we get
that sort of context, an immediate נבואה, nevuah, one by the issue
of defending משה's Moshe. honor, why יהושע Yehoshua had to defend משה's
Moshe honor, and one future prophecy.
גמרא Gemara goes back. אמר מר כל הנביאים כולם נתנבאו ופסקו והם
נתנבאו ולא פסקו. Amar mar: kol hanevi'im kulam nitnabu v'pasaku, v'hem nitnabu
velo pasaku. מנלן דפסקו? Manalan d'pasaku? How do you know the other
נביאים nevi'im stopped?
אילימא מדכתיב ויתנבאו ולא יספו? ilima midechtiv vayitnabu velo yasafu? That was
by the other seventy they prophesied and we're reading ולא יספו velo
yasafu and they
didn't, excuse me I got it mixed up again.
No, I'm right. ויתנבאו ולא יספו Vayitnabu velo yasafu is by those
seventy. So ולא יספו velo yasafu means that they did not continue.
We're reading the word
להוסיף. lehosif. מדכתיב ויתנבאו ולא יספו midechtiv vayitnabu velo yasafu those seventy
prophesied and they did not continue, they were not מוסיף, mosif, it
ended. אלא מעתה קול גדול ולא יסף? Ela me'ata: kol gadol velo
yasaf? By הר סיני, Har Sinai, a great voice ולא יסף, velo
yasaf, do you mean that it did not continue, that it like
ended? הכי נמי דלא אוסיף? hacha nami d'lo osif? Do you mean
to say it did not add on, it ended? התם דהוא פוסק.
Hatam d'hu posek. There the word ולא יסף velo yasaf is not
from the word להוסיף lehosif but the word לאסוף le'esof to gather
in, it did not stop. So if that's true, ויתנבאו ולא יספו
vayitnabu velo yasafu by the seventy should be that it didn't stop.
פה אלא poh ela fine that's not how you're going to learn.
The word ולא יספו velo yasafu is open to whether it means
they did not continue or they did not stop. It could mean
either. So we can't learn it from that.
דהתם כתיב ויתנבאו d'hatam ktiv vayitnabu by the seventy it says they
prophesied in the past. התם כתיב Hatam ktiv and by אלדד ומידד
Eldad uMedad it says מתנבאים, mitnabim, they are prophesying. The gerund I
guess in the present, אדין או עדיין, adayin o adayin, עדיין מתנבאים
והולכים, adayin mitnabim v'holchim, it's still going on. Fine. That's the difference.
Now let's see what the prophecy was. בשלמא למאן דאמר משה מת:
Bishlama leman d'amar Moshe met: היינו דכתיב אדוני משה כלאם. hainu dechtiv
Adoni Moshe kla'em. That's why he was trying
to protect משה's Moshe. honor, so lock them up or destroy them.
אלא להנך תרתי ela l'hanech tarti but if it's these other two,
מה אדוני משה כלאם? ma Adoni Moshe kla'em? What was he doing
there? Why did he want to either, whatever that means, destroy them,
lock them up? What was the big deal? לאו אורח ארעא. lav
orech ar'a. It's not appropriate for them to prophesy in the presence
of משה. Moshe דהוה ליה כתלמיד המורה הלכה לפני רבו. d'havei leh
k'talmid hamoreh halacha lifnei rabo. It's like a פוסק paskening in the
presence of your רבי. משה Moshe is the prime נביא, navi, you
don't give a prophecy in the presence of משה. Moshe Fine.
בשלמא למאן דאמר הנך תרתי Bishlama leman d'amar hanech tarti to say
those two: היינו דכתיב מי יתן hainu dechtiv mi yiten like when
משה Moshe said oh if
anyone. כי יתן ה׳ רוחו עליהם ki yitein Hashem rucho aleihem because
then it's a prophecy that's worth prophesying about that משה could be
happy about. אלא למאן דאמר משה מת, ella leman d'amar Moshe meis,
מן הא הוי ניחא ליה? min ha hava nicha lei? But if
they say משה was going to die, why would they say oh,
if only everybody was a נביא? navi? Of course that could really
show his עניוות, anivus, you know, you want God's spirit to be
with the people even if it says things you don't want to
hear. But the גמרא Gemara has a different answer. It says לא
סיימוה קמיה. lo siyumuha kamei. They didn't tell משה what they were
saying. They just said they were prophesying but they didn't say the
content of it.
So מאי כלאם? mai kela'im? What does it mean by כלאם? kela'im?
Does it mean like put them in a כלא, keleh, lock them
up, destroy them? אמר ליה הטיל עליהם צרכי ציבור. amar lei hatil
aleihem tzorchei tzibur. No, no, no, here's what he was saying. Just
put them in a position of communal responsibility. והן כלין מאליהן. ve-hein
kalin mei-aleihen. And that'll destroy them. As תוספות Tosafos says, it'll destroy
the נבואה. nevuah. You look at תוספות פירש נבואתם כלה. Tosafos peirush
nevuatam kalah. כלה. kalah. דאין שכינה שורה מתוך עצבות אלא מתוך שמחה.
d'ein Shechinah shorah mitoch atzvus ella mitoch simchah. God's presence is not
for somebody that's anguished and sad, and that's certainly going to happen
if you have to worry about leadership of the community.
Okay, now מניין להביא עוד שלשה? minayin lehavi od sheloshah? Now how
do you, you have 10 and 10 and הציבור ועדה ha-tzibur ve-eidah
whatever, you know, ושפטו העדה והצילו העדה ve-shafetu ha-eidah ve-hitzilu ha-eidah and
three more. Okay, and that had to do with this whole figuring
out about that it shouldn't be an even בית דין. Beis Din
Because you need two to be a majority for a דיני נפשות.
dinei nefashos. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, that's not going
to work. So the גמרא Gemara says סוף סוף לרוב פי שנים
לא משכחת לה. sof sof le-rov pi shenayim lo meshkachat lah. Of
23, you're never going to have a בית דין beis din that's
going to be decided for somebody for bad, you know, for דיני
נפשות dinei nefashos with just a majority of two. אי חד סר
מזכין ושתים עשר מחייבין, ei chad sar mazkin u-shneim asar mechayivin, if
it's 11 against 12, אכתי חדא הוא, achati chada hu, that's just
one. אי עשרה מזכין ושלשה עשר מחייבין, ei asarah mazkin u-sheloshah asar
mechayivin, 10 against 13, plus אהא בי תלתא? aha bi tlata? So
אמר רבי אבהו אי אתה מוצא אלא במוסיפין ודברי הכל. amar Rabbi
Abbahu ei attah motzei ella be-mosifin u-divrei ha-kol. The case is that
one person basically says I don't know, which effectively is like recusing
themselves, and therefore we have to add two more. But once one
person says I don't know and you're down to 22 and we
only add in pairs and now we're up to 24 an even
number, now you can have 12 against 10.
And that goes according to all opinions that you would add in
pairs. ובסנהדרי גדולה אליבא דרבי יהודה. u-ve-Sanhedrin gedolah aliba d'Rabbi Yehudah. According
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah that the big סנהדרין Sanhedrin, is 70,
there too you could get 36 against 34.
ואמר שבעים. v'amar shivim. Okay. ואמר רבי אבהו במוסיפין עושין בית דין
שקול לכתחילה. v'amar Rabbi Abbahu be-mosifin oisin beis din shakol le-chatchilah. When
you have to add because one person basically excused themselves, so you're
going to be okay with a בית דין שקול. beis din shakol.
Effectively it'll be 24 now. פשיטא. pishita. Obviously, that's exactly what happens
when you have to add. No, מהו דתימא אימת דקאמר איני יודע,
mahu d'teima eimas d'ka'amar eini yodeiah, the one that says I don't
know, כמאן דאיתיה דמי. k'man d'iseih damei. It's like he's still present.
It's still like there's a בית דין of 23 and that you
really do have an odd number. ואי אמר מילתא שמעינן ליה. v'ei
amar milta sham'inan lei. And then maybe he can go and the
second round, after you've added, maybe now he could cast his vote.
קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that he cannot. So this is
very interesting. Once one person says I don't know, you really basically
is like you've eliminated yourself.
כמאן דליתיה דמי. k'man d'leiseih damei. It's like he's not there. ואי
אמר טעמא לא שמעינן ליה. v'ei amar ta'ama lo sham'inan lei. Even
if afterwards you want to participate, you're not there. It sounds like
not only can you not vote, it even sounds like we don't
even listen to you, which is pretty harsh. Okay. אמר רב כהנא
סנהדרי שראו כולן לחובה. amar Rav Kahana Sanhedrin she-rau kullan le-chovah. This
is a line that a lot of people know. If everybody immediately
voted that the guy is guilty, פוטרין אותו. potrin oso. You exempt
the guy. מאי טעמא? This probably is echoing the ושפטו העדה והצילו
העדה. ve-shafetu ha-eidah ve-hitzilu ha-eidah. You need somebody to try to argue
on his behalf. So כיון דגמירי, keivan d'gemiri, we have a tradition,
that הלנת דין, halanas din, ללמד עליו זכות, le-lammed alav zechus, that
you need to sleep on it overnight in order to think before
you put somebody, make somebody liable to the death penalty, in order
that you have a chance to maybe reflect and find some argument
on his behalf. So it's really important that it not be, you
know, like a predetermined outcome and that there's somebody thinking about and
arguing on his behalf. So in that case, in this case, when
everybody opened up that he's guilty, והני תו לא חזו ליה, ve-hanei
tu lo chazu lei, then nobody will try to argue once it
was unanimous at the outset.
Fine. אמר רבי יוחנן אין מושיבין בסנהדרי אלא בעלי קומה. amar Rabbi
Yochanan ein moshivin be-Sanhedrin ella ba'alei komah. You only, בעלי, ba'alei, this
probably means ideal, not literally that this is an absolute requirement as
we'll see later. But anyway, only people of height, so there goes
stature, that eliminates me. פירושו peirush means it literally. ובעלי חכמה, u-va'alei
chochmah, people who are wise. ובעלי מראה, u-va'alei mareh, they have to
be good-looking. רבי יוחנן was actually good-looking. But anyway, again it's sad
and funny and important and whatever, you know, and understandable that, you
know, some of the qualifications here are very much physical qualifications because
people do wind up, we're human beings, like why the בית המקדש
Beis Ha-Mikdash has to be beautiful. beautiful and gold and so on?
האיש יראה לעינים וה' יראה ללבב, Ha'ish yireh la'einayim v'Hashem yireh laleivav,
but nevertheless we're still human, so we respond differently to people that
are tall and good looking. So it's interesting here that that's being
listed as a criteria. ובעלי זקנה, U'ba'alei zikna, they have to be
old, but presumably also wise, sagacious.
ובעלי כשפים, U'ba'alei kishafim, they have to know witchcraft. רש"י says in
order to counteract witchcraft that other people, that some of the the
defendants might be doing. ויודעים בשבעים לשון, V'yod'im b'shiv'im lashon, know 70
languages. Again, whether it literally means all 70 languages, whether it means
that everybody has to know or some people on the סנהדרין Sanhedrin,
have to know, we'll see later that only some have to know,
not everybody. Okay, שלא תהא סנהדרין שומעת מפי המתורגמן, Shelo tehei Sanhedrin
shoma'as mipi hamisurgeman, but at least somebody's got to know the languages
so that you don't trust only the translator to accurately tell you
what people are saying, and at least some if not all the
members of the בית דין have heard directly. אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב אין מושיבין בסנהדרין אלא מי שיודע לטהר את השרץ. Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, ein moshivin b'Sanhedrin ella mi sheyodei'a l'taher es hasheretz.
Another famous line. Somebody has to be able to make an argument,
a counterfactual argument, to say that a שרץ sheretz is טהור tahor
מן התורה. min haTorah. אמר רב אני אדון ואטהרנו. Amar Rav, ani
adun v'ataharenu. I'll show you how you can do that. ומה נחש
שממית ומרבה טומאה טהור, U'mah nachash shemameis u'marbeh tumah tahor, a snake
kills people, kills animals, and a dead corpse causes טומאה. tumah. And
nevertheless a snake is טהור. tahor. So שרץ שאינו ממית, sheretz she'eino
mameis, a שרץ sheretz that doesn't, like a rodent,
kill, ומרבה טומאה, u'marbeh tumah, and he doesn't cause death and
טומאה, tumah, אינו דין שיהא טהור? eino din sheyehei tahor? So look,
here would be a way you could do it. ולא היא. V'lo
hi. The גמרא Gemara says, you know what? That's actually not a
good argument.
מידי דהוה אקוץ בעלמא. Midi dehavei akoitz b'alma. A thorn also kills
people and that's טהור. tahor. So clearly anyway the idea of whether
you kill people or not kill people is not a factor in
טהור tahor and טומאה. tumah. Now the question is why is the
גמרא Gemara saying that you have to be able to be מטהר
שרץ? metaher sheretz? רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam תוספות Tosafos says מה לנו
לדרשא של הבל. Mah lanu l'drasha shel hevel. Why are you trying
to sort of prove something counterfactual? But to a certain degree what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is sort of like the devil quoting
scripture, you know, that you can always argue
counterfactual. So how do you know if somebody is,
just because somebody can make an argument doesn't mean that they're right.
If you even work with the same sources and you come up
with something that is wrong, that's wrong and that's perverting the meaning
of the law. So it points to the idea that in addition
to being smart what you really need is integrity and character and
honesty and a sense of fidelity to the
תורה Torah and to what your belief of what the תורה Torah
is truly saying. So I think that that's sort of the subtext
here. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
כל עיר שאין בה שנים לדבר ואחד לשמוע.
Kol ir she'ein bah
shnayim l'daber v'echad lishmo'a. If you don't have two people that can
speak a foreign language and one person who can understand it in
addition to those two, אין מושיבין בה סנהדרין. ein moshivin bah Sanhedrin.
Then you cannot have a סנהדרין. Sanhedrin You need at least that
amount of people being able and maybe to be on the סנהדרין
Sanhedrin. to directly hear and communicate with people who speak a different
language. So again it's not everybody on the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin or maybe
this is a local סנהדרין, Sanhedrin two or one is enough. לסנהדרין
גדולה L'Sanhedrin Gedolah at least ideally we want everybody to have it.
ובביתר היו שלש וביבנה ארבע. U'v'Beitar hayu shalosh u'v'Yavneh arba. In ביתר
Beitar there were three who could do this, and in יבנה Yavneh
there were four. רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע ורבי עקיבא ושמעון התימני דן
לפניהם בקרקע. Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Yehoshua v'Rabbi Akiva v'Shimon haTimni dan lifneihem
b'karka. And the four in יבנה Yavneh were רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, and שמעון התימני Shimon
haTimni who doesn't have a רבי, he didn't have סמיכה, smicha, and
he was a student, and he was on the ground, and he
was participating in the deliberations but he did not have סמיכה smicha
yet. Those were the ones in יבנה Yavneh who knew all the
languages. מיתיבי, Meisivi, I'll ask you, שלישי חכמה רביעי אין למעלה הימנו.
Shlishi chochma revi'i ein l'ma'alah heimenu. If the third one can have,
know the languages, three know the languages, that's wisdom, four, that you'll
never get anything like it. And here you said that it's enough
that it's two. Okay. הוא דאמר Hu d'amar כי האי תנא, ki
hai tanna,
דתני
לשני חכמה לשלישי אין למעלה הימנו. detani lishnei chochma lishlishi ein l'ma'ala
heimenu. Fine. Now that we've mentioned this idea of דן לפניהם בקרקע,
dan lifneihem b'karka, we're going to have a little pure digression to
talk about, but it's not really a digression because it talks about
identifying the different rabbis. We're in the middle of סנהדרין and different
statuses, סנהדרין גדולה, סנהדרין קטנה, Sanhedrin Ketanah, and we're going to talk
about which phrases that talks about rabbis, which rabbis they're referring to.
So let's take a look. So it says like this.
למידים לפני חכמים, Lemidim lifnei chachamim, when it says this person was
sort of learning in front of the sages, that's לוי מרבי, Levi
miRebbi, לוי Levi who was learning from רבי. That's what למידים לפני
חכמים lemidim lifnei chachamim always refers to, לוי Levi learning from רבי.
דנים לפני חכמים, Danim lifnei chachamim, deliberating in front of the sages,
שמעון בן עזאי ושמעון בן זומא וחנן המצרי וחנניה בן חכינאי. Shimon
ben Azzai v'Shimon ben Zoma v'Chanan haMitzri v'Chananyah ben Chakinai. Notice they
don't have the word רבי. They were students, but they were on
the floor and they were part of the deliberations. רב נחמן בר
יצחק מתני חמשה, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak masni chamisha, five, שמעון, שמעון,
שמעון, Shimon Shimon Shimon, the two שמעון Shimon you mentioned plus the
one שמעון Shimon that we mentioned earlier at יבנה, Yavneh, which was
שמעון התימני. Shimon haTimni. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
מוסיף חמישה, mosif chamisha, five. שמעון Shimon שמעון Shimon שמעון, the two
שמעוןs just mentioned plus the one שמעון that we mentioned earlier at
יבנה, Yavneh, which was שמעון התימני, Shimon HaTeimani, חנן וחנניה, Chanan ve'Chananya,
five. רבותינו שבבבל, Rabboseinu she'be-Bavel, the phrase רבותינו שבבבל, Rabboseinu she'be-Bavel, who
does that refer to? רב ושמואל. Rav ve'Shmuel. רבותינו שבארץ ישראל, Rabboseinu
she'be-Eretz Yisrael, who does that refer to? רבי אבא ורבי אמי. Rebbi
Abba ve'Rebbi Ami. Okay, it's interesting it's in the plural. Okay. דייני
גולה, dayyanei golah, the judges of the exile, קרנא. Karna. דייני ארץ
ישראל, dayyanei Eretz Yisrael, רבי אמי ורבי אסי. Rebbi Ami ve'Rebbi Assi.
דייני דפומבדיתא, dayyanei de'Pumbedisa, who are the judges of Pumbedisa? רב פפא
בר שמואל. Rav Pappa bar Shmuel.
It's only one. דייני דנהרדעא, dayyanei de'Neharde'a, רב אדא בר מניומי. Rav
Adda bar Minyumi. Okay, so those are what those phrases, the judges
of Neharde'a, that's refers to him. סבי דסורא, sabei de'Sura, the elders
of Sura, רב הונא ורב חסדא. Rav Huna ve'Rav Chisda. רב סבי
דפומבדיתא, Rav sabei de'Pumbedisa, the elders of
Pumbedisa, רב יהודה ורב עינא. Rav Yehuda ve'Rav Eina. חריפי דפומבדיתא, charifei
de'Pumbedisa, the sharp ones of Pumbedisa, עיפא ואבימי בני רחבה. Eifa ve'Avimi
benei Rechava. אמוראי דפומבדיתא, amora'ei de'Pumbedisa, the Amoraim, רבה ורב יוסף, Rabba
ve'Rav Yosef, as we know, the major Amoraim. Okay. אמוראי דנהרדעא, amora'ei
de'Neharde'a, the Amoraim of Neharde'a, רב חמא מנהרבלאי Rav Chama mi-Neharbalai from
this place Neharbal. Okay. מתני, masni, when it says they taught, that's
רמי בר ברבי. Rami bar Berabi. Okay, when it says אמרי בי
רב, amri bei Rav, when they say
it was said in the house of Rav, so that was רב
הונא. Rav Huna. That's רב הונא Rav Huna who said it. דאמר
רב הונא אמרי בי רב. de'amar Rav Huna amri bei Rav. Wait,
you can't say that because we have a line, we have a
tradition that Rav Huna said that they said in the house of
Rav. So אמרי בי רב amri bei Rav can't mean רב הונא.
Rav Huna. אלא רב המנונא, ella Rav Hamnuna, fine, it means Rav
Hamnuna. There's a debate רש"י תוספות, Rashi Tosafos, says בי רב bei
Rav mean רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna or did רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna
say אמרי בי רב amri bei Rav and בי רב bei Rav
is still רב הונא. Rav Huna. אמרי במערבא, amri be'ma'arava, they say
in Eretz Yisrael, so who is that?
רבי ירמיה. Rebbi Yirmiya. שלחו מתם, shalchu misam, they sent from there
from Eretz Yisrael, רבי יוסי בר חנינא. Rebbi Yosi bar Chanina. מחכו
עליה במערבא, machaku aleih be'ma'arava, they mocked this in the west in
Israel, רבי אלעזר, Rebbi Elazar, רב אלעזר. Rav Elazar. So the Gemara
says one minute, והא שלחו מתם, ve-ha shalchu misam, you can't say
shalchu misam is רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rebbi Yosi bar Chanina because
we have a case where it says they sent from there ודברי
רבי יוסי בר חנינא, u-divrei Rebbi Yosi bar Chanina, saying something according
to Rebbi Yosi bar Chanina, referencing him. So clearly it's not Rebbi
Yosi bar Chanina. So the Gemara says אלא איפכא, ella ipcha, fine,
reverse it. שלחו מתם shalchu misam is רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, מחכו
עליה במערבא, machaku aleih be'ma'arava, that's רבי יוסי בר חנינא. Rebbi Yosi
bar Chanina. So that was quite snappy. Let's just finish up the
פרק. perek. מאה ועשרים, me'ah ve'esrim, a hundred, a hundred and twenty
according to the חכמים Chachamim that you need of people in the
city in order to make a סנהדרין.
So it says, so מאה
ועשרים, me'ah ve'esrim, מאי עבידתייהו, mai avidtaihu,
where do you get that? עשרים ושלושה כנגד סנהדרין קטנה esrim u-shlosha
ke'neged Sanhedrin ketana because you need twenty-three to be on the Sanhedrin,
ושלושה שורות של עשרים ושלושה, u-shlosha shuros shel esrim u-shlosha, and we're
going to learn that in Sanhedrin they would have like, you know,
replacements, twenty-three, three groups of twenty-three that if people had to leave
or whatever they could replace them. So now we have four times
twenty-three is ninety-two, הרי תשעים ושניים, harei tishim u-shenayim, ועשרה בטלנים, va'asara
batlanim, ten batlanim של בית הכנסת shel beis ha'knesses that are always
ready to make a minyan, הרי מאה ושניים, harei me'ah u-shenayim, ושני
סופרים ושני חזנים, u-shenei sofrim u-shenei chazanim, two scribes, two like, you
know, attendant people that like clerks, ושני בעלי דינין, u-shenei ba'alei dinin,
and two litigants, ושני עדים, u-shenei eidim, two witnesses, ושני זוממין, u-shenei
zomemin, two witnesses that can make them zomemin, ושני זוממי זוממין, u-shenei
zomemei zomemin, הרי מאה וארבעים. harei me'ah ve'arba'im. That gets you a
hundred and forty, it's not 120. Okay, so you need a city
of 120 so it has all of the normal pieces and functions
of the city to support and only that city is deserving of
a בית דין of twenty-three. But anyway, how do you get the
remaining six? So בתניא, bitanya, כל עיר שאין בה עשרה דברים הללו,
kol ir she'ein bah asara devarim halalu, a city, a town, really
an עיר is a town, that doesn't have these ten things, אין
תלמיד חכם רשאי לדור בתוכה. ein talmid chacham rasha'i ladur be-sochah. And
what is that? בית דין מכין ועונשין, beis din makin ve'onshin, a
beis din, so we've already mentioned a beis din, וקופה של צדקה,
u-kuppah shel tzedakah, נגבית בשניים ומתחלקת בשלושה, nigbis bi-shnayim u-mis-chalekes bi-shlosha, you
need charity funds which is collected with two and distributed with three,
so that's five more jobs. So now we're up to 119. Okay,
בית הכנסת ובית המרחץ ובית הכיסא. beis ha'knesses u-veis ha'merchatz u-veis ha'kisei.
Okay, so all of those, you know, a shul, a bathhouse, an
outhouse, רופא ואומן ולבלר, rofe ve'uman ve'lavlar, a doctor, a bloodletter, a
scribe, טבח, tabbach, a butcher if you have that גרסא, girsa, ומלמד
תינוקות u-melammed tinokos and a schoolteacher. So of course that gets you
more than 120 but Rashi said one person could do all those
jobs. משום רבי עקיבא אמרו, mishum Rebbi Akiva amru, אף מיני פירות.
af minei peiros. No, you need also some nice different fruit, מפני
שמיני פירות מאיורין את העיניים, mipnei she-minei peiros me'irin es ha'einayim, that
helps to, you know, to give you the right frame of mind
in order to be to learn Torah well. Last piece, רבי נחמיה
אומר, Rebbi Nechemiah omer, the city has to have 230, מאתיים ושלושים,
masayim u-shloshim, so that each one is fit to be a head
of a
ten. Okay, תניא, רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, מאתיים ושבעים ושבעה, masayim ve'shiv'im
ve'shiv'ah, 277. ותניא רבי, ve-tanya Rebbi, so where do you get that?
So it starts with the 230 like Rebbi Nechemiah, but you add
47 because you could
have to add
to
beis din. 230 plus
47. והא
תניא V'ha tanya רבי אומר Rebbi omer מאתיים ושבעים ושמונה masayim v'shivim
v'shmona 278. לא קשיא הא רבי יהודה הא רבנן.
Lo kashya ha
Rebbi Yehuda ha Rabbanan. It depends whether a big סנהדרין is 70
or 71 because you would grow a 23 that was hung up
to the size of a סנהדרין whether there's 70 or 71. Okay,
תנו רבנן ושמת עליהם v'samta aleihem שרי אלפים sarei alafim שרי מאות
sarei meos שרי חמישים sarei chamishim שרי עשרות. sarei asaros. So שרי
אלפים sarei alafim gets you שש מאות shesh meos 600. שרי מאות
sarei meos ששת אלפים sheshes alafim 6,000. שרי חמישים sarei chamishim שנים
עשר אלף shneim asar elef 12,000. שרי עשרות sarei asaros שש ריבוא
shesh ribo 60,000. נמצאו דייני ישראל nimtzau dayanei Yisrael the judges of
Israel in the time of Moshe were שבע ריבוא ושמונת אלפים ושש
מאות sheva ribo u'shmonas alafim v'shesh meos 78,600.
And with that we end the first פרק. perek.